<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The absolute truth, and utmost certainty of the word of God and that all things which are contained in the scriptures, yea to every tittle and iota thereof, will be fulfiled : demonstrated in a discourse on Rom IX. 6 / by Richard Stafford ...</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5107F</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475313</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2257:4e, 2827:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The absolute truth, and utmost certainty of the word of God and that all things which are contained in the scriptures, yea to every tittle and iota thereof, will be fulfiled : demonstrated in a discourse on Rom IX. 6 / by Richard Stafford ...</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32, 15, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Ralph Simpson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIX [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in: Dr. Williams' Library (London, England), and Magdalene College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
                  <note>With: The exceeding great comfort and benefit of having walked before God in truth, and with a perfect heart / by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ... MDCXCIX [1699] -- Sermon I. on Phil. IV. 11 / written by Richard Stafford. [London] : Printed at London, 1698 (Wing S5131C) -- The necessity of keeping still unto the ordinances of religion. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., 1698 (Wing S5126) -- A sermon on 2 Cor. 2. XI / written by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., MDCXCVIII [1698] (Wing S5131B) -- Hear this word, o ye princes, ye priests and people of England. [London : s.n., 1698] (Wing S5120).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans IX, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151379:1"/>
            <p>THE Abſolute Truth, and Utmoſt Certainty OF THE <hi>Word of God:</hi> AND That all Things which are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scriptures, yea to every Tittle and Iota thereof, will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Demonſtrated in a Diſcourſe on <hi>Rom.</hi> IX. 6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD,</hi> formerly of <hi>Magdalen-Hall</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 55. 10, 11.</bibl>
               <p>For as the Rain cometh down, and the Snow from Heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the Earth, and maketh it to bring forth and bud, that it may give Seed to the Sower, and Bread to the Eater. So ſhall my Word be that goeth forth out of my mouth, it ſhall not return unto me void, but it ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the Thing whereto I ſent it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London.</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Ralph Simpſon,</hi> at the <hi>Harp</hi> in St. Paul's Church-Yard. MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:151379:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151379:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. IX. 6.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Not as though the Word of God hath taken none effect.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ONE of the Greateſt Prejudices againſt the Preaching and Publiſhing of the Word of God is, in that ſo very few are converted by it, and do Obey it. Let Men Preach till their Hearts ake (as the common Proverbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Speech is) and tire out their Lungs, ſpend their ſtrength, yea, <hi>Seek out acceptable Words,</hi> as <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes</hi> did, and do all that ever they can in the work of the Miniſtry, both by <hi>ſtudying in Gods Statutes</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice was, and alſo by Prayer and Diligent Labour; yet ſtill the World will not be Reformed, nor brought off from their lees of Corruption and Iniquity. They will go on in their old former ways, Ungodlineſs and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, let the Miniſters and Servants of God ſay and do whatever they can. Therefore it is, that the Word is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the Weakneſs of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 25. In that it is deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be unable and inſufficient to effect the very thing it doth intend at, that is, to bring People over unto the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Law of God, and to Regulate their lives and manners.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Commandment is Holy, Juſt and Good in it ſelf; Thy Precepts concerning all things are Right,</hi> Yet here lies the great ſtumbling Block and Rock of offence, which quite keeps off the ungodly and mixt Multitude from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151379:3"/> getting over it, and the ſteps of Good and Faithful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do <hi>well nigh ſlip thereat,</hi> In that, Notwithſtanding it is ſo little obeyed, and ſo very little heed is given unto them by the Generality of People. They will indeed talk of the Commandments of God, and make a ſhew as if they had <hi>performed 1 Sam.</hi> 15. 13. And were guided thereby, but all along and in the mean while, <hi>They do walk in a way that is not good after their own thoughts,</hi> Iſa. 65. 2. And according to their own Will, Humour, Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Imaginations. It is a common ſaying, that People will have their Will whatever it coſt them: And it is to be feared (as there is real Ground for this Surmiſe, from the Word of God) that too many are bent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon their own Will though they ſhould be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or condemned for it at the Day of Judgment, and it coſt them no leſs than <hi>the Loſs of their precious Immortal Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVe read in the Old Teſtament, of <hi>the Lords Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with his people;</hi> and this is the Controverſie which he hath with the Inhabitants of the Earth, VVhether they ſhall do according to his VVord and Commandments, and be led by the ſilent and inward Dictates of his Spirit. Or they think, ſpeak and practice, for the heart of every one of them is deep: <hi>Our Lips are our own; VVho is Lord over us?</hi> Thoughts are free, according to their own Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal and Imagination. And ſo it is of the Words and Actions in the Children of Diſobedience, They ſpeak and do as they liſt. This is a Controvercy which at the laſt will be decided to the Creatures Puniſhment and Miſery.</p>
            <p>The Pſalmiſt doth ſpeak further of the people of his Generation; <hi>They corrupt others, and ſpeak of Wicked Blaſphemy; Their Talking is againſt the Moſt High.</hi> There is indeed that Knowledge, and Outward Worſhip, and inward Reverential Eſteem, Univerſally received amongſt the people of this Nation, that hardly any, unleſs ſome very few Debauch'd, and Ignorant Young Men of the Richer ſort, do talk directly and immediately againſt God himſelf; For this would be ſo odious and deteſtable, that even <hi>the Common Multitude</hi> would not bear it. But if they do not ſpeak out, becauſe that <hi>they profeſs that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151379:3"/> they know God, but in Works they deny him.</hi> But they think and Act to the very ſame purpoſe. God ſees and knows the thoughts all one, as if they were wrote in Great Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon the Foreheads of thoſe who did conceive them. And he doth make alike conſtruction of their Actions, as if they did ſpeak out the ſame what thoſe Actions do Import.</p>
            <p>Things are confuſed and ſeem perplex through the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Sinners and Hypocrites. By the former of which, I mean thoſe who are open Barefaced and Manifeſtly Sinners; Who will own that they Commit Sin and Tranſgreſſion, and make excuſes for it; and cry out. <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> or the like. By Hypocrites, I intend ſuch who obſerve all the Parts and ſeaſons of the Worſhip of God, and other things pertaining to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet they live in the Breach and Neglect of ſome of the Commandments of God. But whilſt they ſeem to be Righteous and Religious when they are not; <hi>And they juſtify themſelves before Men,</hi> whereas God knoweth the heart; <hi>And what is highly eſteemed amongſt Men, is an Abomination in his ſight;</hi> Whilſt they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves and call themſelves Godly and <hi>Lean on the Lord,</hi> Micah 3. 11. As Counterfeit Gold doth ſometimes Shine and Gliſter more then true: So they Profeſs more Honour and Obedience to God then perhaps his very Elect and Real Servants, Hence our way is the more intricate to trace and find them out, then thoſe who are downright Sinners and Ungodly. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever are the doings of all the Children of Men, the Word of God doth find them out; And however the Rebellious and Diſobedient would render it ineffectual and uſeleſs, that is not binding and obligatory to them, and that it ſhould be rather falſified then ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, when it ſpeaks of Mens obedience unto Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; for as for their Part, they will not yield it. As we ſee and obſerve theſe things in the World, we are not thence to doubt in our own Mind; But it theſe and ſuch like things, ſtill we may have Recourſe to this great Aſſertion of the Apoſtle, <hi>Not as tho the Word of God hath taken none effect, for they are not all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which are of</hi> Iſrael. That is, They are nor all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151379:4"/> Servants of God, who have the Name and pretend to be ſo, or do herd themſelves in their Number.</p>
            <p>I did therefore chooſe and thought Good to inſiſt upon theſe Words, chiefly, if not for the Removal (for it will ſtill abide and remain) yet for the right underſtanding of that firſt Prejudice, which in the very beginning lies againſt the Word of God; In that ſo very few are converted by it and do obey it; That ye who do believe and obey to the ſaving of your Souls, be not ſoon <hi>ſhaken in Mind,</hi> by the Diſadvantages which ariſe thereby; for it may anon appear, that this is yet a greater fulfilling of the ſame Word.</p>
            <p>As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth record of himſelf, <hi>That after the manner of Men, he had fought with Beaſts at Epheſus:</hi> So both in the beginning, entrance and courſe of our Miniſtry (which is more advanced and carried on by Writing, Printing and Publiſhing then by ſpeaking with a living Voice; For whereas the Voice Periſhes in the utterance and the matter is ſoon forgotten by the Hearer, that reaches to the People afar off and to after Ages) I ſay again, that both in the beginning and courſe of our Miniſtry, we have met with <hi>Scoffers,</hi> who with their ſeveral kinds of ſayings, did endeavour either to turn us aſide from our intended Miniſtry, or to defeat the deſign thereof. As it was ſaid to <hi>Ezekiel, Thou art not ſent to a People of ſtrange Speech and of an hard Language, but to the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Not to many People of a ſtrange Speech and of an hard Language, whoſe Words thou canſt not underſtand. Surely, had I ſent thee to them, they would have hearkened to thee. But the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>will not hearken unto thee, for they will not hearken unto me. For all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>are impudent and hard hearted,</hi> Ezek. 3. 5, 6, 7. So if I ſhould recount my manifold Experiences, I ſhould make known that I have met with more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and contrary uſage, Evil entreaty, contradiction and falſe Reproaches from Formal and Nominal Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and from outward Worſhippers, then ever I did from open Sinners and the manifeſt Ungodly: Tho' I have ſpoken equally againſt their Sin and Ungodlineſs, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151379:4"/> I have laid open the Hypocriſie and Fooliſh vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the others. And yet all this doth nothing ſhake me in Mind, nor yet doth it at all abate or leſſen from my preſent Comfort in the well grounded hope of my future acceptance from the Lord. But rather it doth increaſe and confirm me therein, <hi>That I may have boldneſs in the Day of Judgment, becauſe as he was, ſo are we in this preſent World.</hi> For the like did happen to him alſo, to be thus oppoſed and contradicted in his Miniſtry by the Scribes and Phariſees (who were the then Teachers and Expounders of the Law) and by the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were as exact and conſtant in all the Parts and Times of the outward worſhip of God all the ſame while, as the People of this Nation do go continually to their Pariſh Churches, or other Congregations and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</p>
            <p>Where the moſt good is either done or intended, there the Devil doth raiſe the greateſt oppoſition; and the old Serpent doth never ſhew himſelf more ſubtle then when he Acts through thoſe who ſeem to be Religious and to make a fair ſhew in the fleſh. So that when the Spirit of Lying and Falſhood or Reproach doth proceed forth through them, it hath a greater Appearance and Likeneſs unto Truth; and ſo it paſſes down glib with them, who judge according to Appearance and not Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord is well pleaſed for his Righteouſneſs ſake, He will magnifie the Law and make it Honourable,</hi> Iſa. 42. 21. And as the Miniſtration thereof is more worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the Buſineſs and Employment of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Kings or wiſeſt States-Men. Nevertheleſs Ignorant and Ungodly Minds, like as when <hi>Michal</hi> ſaw <hi>David</hi> Dancing before the Ark, ſhe deſpiſed him: So they will leſſen and have a low eſteem of ſuch a kind of Office. Or as they Proudly and Diſdainfully think, that it is not conſiſtent with a Good Birth and Education. Alas! All theſe and ſuch like are but fooliſh and falſe Imaginations, which Satan ſuggeſts and keeps in the Minds of ſome People for to uphold his Kingdom. It is all but Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and nothing of reality therein, for as it is ſaid in the Book of <hi>Job, I am alſo formed out of the Clay. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151379:5"/> the Governour of the Province ſpeaks in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Poor, <hi>Yet now our fleſh is as the fleſh of our Brathren, our Children as their Children,</hi> Neh. 5. 5. <hi>God hath made of one Blood</hi> (obſerve that) <hi>all Nations of Men, for to dwell on the Face of the Earth,</hi> Acts 17. 26. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in then doth one differ from and excell another, even in reſpect of theſe vile Bodies, whilſt we are in the midſt of Life and carry them about us, all one as when they come to be in the place of Skulls, where the Poor and Rich are all alike. And whereas the Richer ſort now a-days call themſelves a good Family, I wiſh that ſin and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and that ſhame which is among them of coming down to the Plainneſs and Simplicity of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or to the place where his Word is Preached, did not manifeſt and demonſtrate the contrary. <hi>He that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, ſhall not be hurt by the ſecond Death.</hi> And this is overcoming that Corruption which is both within our own Nature, and alſo that which is in the World through the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eyes and the Pride of Life. And truly, if the Pride of Life was overcome and rooted out of the minds of any one, as it is out of every one who is indeed the Child and Servant of God and an Heir of Glory; then all thoſe things that Savour of Men; All thoſe Imaginations and Sayings which ariſe up from the Pride and Faſhion of this World, or from the chief that is from the Rich People thereof, will all ſink and fall to the ground, and be as dung in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion of the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, or what may further his Goſpel in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 1. 16. What need had the Apoſtle to ſay this? But only in Relation and Anſwer to thoſe who would imagine and faſten ſhame thereon, in order to diſſwade from what was Good and Praiſe worthy. The Devil Acts in the minds of People to endeavour to beat off, or let and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one who may be a proper Inſtrument and Labourer in the Work and Vineyard of the Lord. But the ſhame wherewith they would reproach that, ſhall at laſt return upon their own heads, when themſelves ſhall at laſt riſe up to Shame and Everlaſting Contempt; And they who were a ſhamed of Chriſt in this Adulterous and Sinful
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151379:5"/> Generation (It is not ſaid, <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Heathen,</hi> but in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithets proper and ſutable to this Countrey of <hi>England</hi> at this Day) of them ſhall the Son of Man be aſhamed, when He cometh in the Glory of his Father with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels.</p>
            <p>People are commonly aſhamed of that whereof a great ſtir and clutter is made before-hand and nothing comes of it. And hereupon it is, that Ignorant Perſons and Unbelievers would endeavour to faſten ſhame on the Preaching of the Goſpel. For as they think and object, the Goſpel imports good tidings and talks of great, yea, the greateſt things in the World, and nothing hereof is ſeen to them nor preſently had. That Reaſon which <hi>Paul</hi> gives in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16. Seems to Anſwer all this to two ſorts of People, the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the Power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to every one that believeth</hi> (Obſerve and Attend well to that) <hi>To the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Greek.</hi> It is therefore ſaid, <hi>To be the Power of God unto Salvation, unto the Jew firſt.</hi> This was to inſtruct and rightly inform him, who did expect Salvation by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; as to which they did both come ſhort, which the Goſpel of Chriſt doth ſupply and make up. The <hi>Jews</hi> were not ſo much Ignorant in Part, as Unbelievers in Part; But the <hi>Greeks</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi> were altogether Unbelievers in the whole. And take them as ſuch, they can no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what this <hi>Power of God unto Salvation is,</hi> then if you talk the ſame unto a Brute Beaſt. And therefore it is fitly put before, <hi>To every one that believeth.</hi> For put the caſe, you ſhould talk of <hi>Salvation</hi> to an Infant or to a Child of a twelvemonth old, Will He underſtand what thou ſayeſt? In no wiſe. So it is, if you talk to a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Indian,</hi> who knows nothing of God or Futurity; and when ſuch an one is in good Plight and Health and hath none but Friends about him, then talk to him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Salvation,</hi> which ſignifies Safety and Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Danger, whereas he ſees and perceives no danger at all. And He will think that the Man is Idle or Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or is Fooliſh, who talk and diſcourſes thereof. It would be near the ſame to acquaint ſome Poor Ungodly Beggars about <hi>Salvation;</hi> If they are Healthy, Luſty and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151379:6"/> Strong, if they have before them a Meal of Good Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and they know where to have another, they do not apprehend much more or beſides this. But they think ſuch an one ſpeaks Parables, or Nonſenſical things unto them.</p>
            <p>It is very obſervable, how it is Uſhered and brought in, <hi>A Brutiſh Man knoweth not, neither doth a Fool underſtand this. When the Wicked Spring as the Graſs, and when all the Workers of Iniquity do flouriſh, It is, that they ſhall be deſtroyed for Ever,</hi> Pſal. 92. 6, 7. So it is, though it be beſides their Opinion and Expectation. In like manner when any of the other Truths of God, or of the things pertaining to his Kingdom come to be declared and ſpoken of, the ſame Preface may be uſed and put before, <hi>A Brutiſh Man knoweth not, neither doth a Fool underſtand this.</hi> So it will be of the things whereof we ſhall by and by ſpeak, <hi>A Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Man knoweth not, neither doth a Fool underſtand this:</hi> It being uſual with the Holy Ghoſt, when He comes to make known things which will hardly meet with Credibility and Reception, to Anticipate and take notice of the ſame before-hand. As <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins after this manner, <hi>Who hath believed our Report?</hi> Importing that very few or none would, until after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they ſhould ſee it fulfilled.</p>
            <p>It is properly and truly expreſſed when ſuch are Termed <hi>Brutiſh Men and Fools;</hi> For tho' they have the ſhape of Men, yet they underſtand no more of the things of God; And thereby alſo we are given to apprehend (for 'tis the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God which gives them this Character) that if they do not uſe that Image of God which he had Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in them, towards the Knowledge of God and of the things pertaining to his Kingdom; They loſe it again, and Notwithſtanding they retain the ſame out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhape with his Saints and Servants, yet in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward likeneſs they are very Brutes. And ſo whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or how much they know beſides if they have not this knowledge alſo, they are in very deed Fools, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hereby and for want thereof they become Subject and Liable unto Loſs and Puniſhment.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151379:6"/>
            <p>Now if I had altogether to do with Brutes and Fools, I ſhould be aſhamed of Preaching the Goſpel, unleſs there were ſome Spiritual People who know of the things whereof we ſpeak; Or unleſs their underſtandings were ſomewhat opened that they could a little conceive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But if the <hi>Myſtery of the Goſpel</hi> be a little opened and made known unto ye, then neither will ye object ſhame, nor yet ſhall I incur ſhame in the Preaching thereof. And in the mean while this is no running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way or beſides from the Text, but it ſhews and confirms all along that the <hi>Word of God hath ſome effect and reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> For whereas People are commonly aſhamed of that, whereof a great clutter and ſtir is made and nothing comes of it. But the <hi>Goſpel is in Word,</hi> and that is not ſo much as in things. <hi>But yet the Goſpel come not to you in Word only, but alſo in Power and in the Holy Ghoſt, and in much aſſurance,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 5. It is much more then in other Words, for thus much is evident and ſenſible, that they have not ſo much Power over the Hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men as this Goſpel hath. Neither were any other Words under Heaven, Accompanied with ſo, many Signs and Miracles and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God himſelf did bear Witneſs to the certainty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of the things contained in this Everlaſting Goſpel. And then it is in much Aſſurance that it ſhall be all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and found true.</p>
            <p>This is the very Reaſon why things ſo go on as they have and do now in the World, <hi>That the Scriptures might be fulfilled;</hi> And therein the <hi>Word of God hath its effect,</hi> Which ſpeaks of things exactly as they are. But here this is to be attended unto, that the Things and Words of God are to be performed and fulfilled <hi>in their Seaſon,</hi> Luke 1. 20. That is according to the Order and Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time, ſome have been already fulfilled, others are now at this Day fulfilling; But the greateſt and moſt things of all are yet to be fulfilled, as in the future State, the Reſurrection of the Dead, the Day of Judgment and the Succeeding Eternity. The thing is certain, tho' the time appointed for it is long. <hi>For the Viſion is yet for an Appointed Time, but at the End it ſhall ſpeak and not lie, tho' it Tarry, Wait for it; Becauſe it will ſurely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151379:7"/> Come, it will not Tarry,</hi> Hab. 2. 3. Gods work as to the Inhabitants of the Earth is a work of ſix or ſeven Thouſand Years continuance, which is a going and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on ever ſince He firſt Created Man on the Earth, during all the while, He who hath called the Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the beginning, hath ordered them to paſs through, all which is but a ſhort time in reſpect to God, to whom a <hi>Thouſand Years are but as one Day,</hi> tho' it be long to us. And accordingly the Scripture ſpeaks of it thus differently both theſe manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> That is, It is ſhort as to God, and long as to us Imperfect Creatures. <hi>For the Lord is not ſlack as concerning his Promiſe, as ſome Men count ſlackneſs for a Thouſand Years, is as one day with the Lord,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 8. <hi>For he will finiſh the Work and cut it ſhort in Righteouſneſs; Becauſe a ſhort Work will the Lord make upon the Earth,</hi> Rom. 9. 28. Yet as to us, the time appointed is long. <hi>Return, O Lord, How long?</hi> Pſal. 90. 13. <hi>And ſhall not God avenge his own Elect, which cry Day and Night unto him, tho' he bear long with them, I tell you, that he will avenge them ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Luke 17. 7, 8. <hi>How long, O Lord, Holy and True, Doſt thou not iudge and avenge our Blood on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> Rev. 6. 10. Tho' it was ſaid ſixteen hundred years ago that God would <hi>avenge them ſpeedily,</hi> it is not done as yet; But tho' it be ſomewhat long as to our Expectation and Deſire, yet it will be ſure at laſt, and it will be all done together, as may be underſtood from the following Verſe here, <hi>And white Robes were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto every one of them, and it was ſaid unto them that they ſhould reſt yet for a little Seaſon, until their fellow Servants alſo and their Brethren that ſhould be killed as they were, ſhould be fulfilled. And ſo the Deſtruction of Sinners and Tranſgreſſours ſhall be together,</hi> Iſa. 1. 28. Even of all Generations and Countreys. So that ſuch being the Decree and Order of God, ye are in no wiſe to think, <hi>Not as tho' the Word of God hath taken none effect,</hi> For it will be all found true in its Seaſon. Not one jot of the Law ſhall paſs away, until all be fulfilled. And not one of the ſayings therein as to future things, ſhall fall to the Ground till it ſhall indeed ſo come to paſs. Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but my Words ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151379:7"/> not paſs away. <hi>The Graſs withereth, the Flower <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but the Word of our God ſhall ſtand for Ever,</hi> Iſa. 40. 8.</p>
            <p>Hereby alſo it may be underſtood, that Unbelievers and the Ignorant Multitude are certainly deceived in their Imaginations. For whereas they Judge very much by Events; And becauſe they ſee no ſuch dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments poured down upon Sinners, <hi>That all things happen alike to all, and continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation:</hi> Men and Women <hi>fall aſleep,</hi> and dye as People uſually do, they think falſely, They may therefore do as they will; It is the Preachers Trade to cry out againſt ſin, but they are vain Words for they come to nothing. Whereas we ſpeak of future Rewards and Puniſhments, and the Time of Deciſion is not yet come. <hi>Son of Man, What is that Proverb that ye have in the Land of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Saying, The Days are Prolonged, and every Viſion faileth, Tell them therefore, thus ſaith the Lord God, I will make this Proverb to ceaſe, and they ſhall no more uſe it as a Proverb in</hi> Iſrael; <hi>but ſay unto them, the Days are at hand and the effect of every Viſion,</hi> Ezek. 12. 22, 23. This Anſwers to the very Words of my Text; For it ſhews that the Word of God hath ſome, and will have yet a greater Effect. As the ſame is again Affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>But the Word which I have ſpoken ſhall be done, ſaith the Lord God,</hi> Ezek. 12. 28. And tho' the Viſion which we ſee <hi>(With the Eyes of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding being enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened) is yet for many Days to come, and we Prophecy of the Times that are afar off, yet they will be preſent and near alſo.</hi> And it is therefore thus ordered by the Wiſdom of God, to prove the Children of Men theſe forty, fifty, or ſixty Years, <hi>To know what is in their Heart, whither they will keep his Commandments or no,</hi> Deu. 8. 2. <hi>And He ſaid I will hide my Face from them, I will ſee what their End ſhall be; for they are a very froward Generation, Children in whom there is no faith,</hi> Deu. 32. 20. <hi>According to the Revelation of the Myſtery</hi> (Mark that) <hi>which was kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſince the World began. But now is made manifeſt, and by the Scriptures of the Prophets, according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Everlaſting God, made known to all Nations for the Obedience of Faith,</hi> Rom. 16. 25, 26. Here is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151379:8"/> Myſtery of God Revealed and Manifeſted (which ſame Myſtery of God at length will be finiſhed as He hath declared to his Servants the Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. 7.) For things were purpoſely ſo ordained to prove all Nations, whither they would yield an Obedience of Faith. That they might <hi>walk by Faith and not by Sight.</hi> And herein the other Scriptures agree and have Relation, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, ſhall not make haſte,</hi> Iſa. 28. 16. Which being twice Quoted by <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Rom. 9. 33. Rom.</hi> 10. 11. The latter Words inſtead of, <hi>ſhall not make haſte, is, ſhall not be aſhamed.</hi> Both put together make up near the ſame Sence and Meaning, and exactly Pertinent to the matter in hand. That is as much as to ſay, <hi>That whoſoever doth know and really believe the things of God in the very order as they ſtand and are Determined, He ſhall not make haſte;</hi> As to think, or go about to get them fulfilled ſooner then their appointed Time. And whoſo is fully perſwaded of and doth embrace them by Faith, He is not aſhamed in this World for following after inviſible and future things; but more eſpecially, He ſhall not be aſhamed (it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the future tence) in the World to come, for they ſhall be Actually given and made Good to the Soul that ſeeketh them.</p>
            <p>By Faith we apprehend and lay hold on theſe Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Promiſes, <hi>And they that be Wiſe</hi> (In the Margent it is, Teachers) <hi>ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as Stars for Ever and Ever,</hi> Dan. 12. 3. <hi>Brethren, if any of you do err from the Truth and one Convert Him. Let him know that He which Converteth a ſinner from the Errour of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, and ſhall hide a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Sins,</hi> James 5. 19. Here it hath been Scoffingly and Sarcaſtically objected unto us, What, you Convert Sinners? They will not be Converted by thee, Go and Convert thoſe at your own Houſe. But Jeſus ſaid unto them, <hi>A Prophet is not without Honour, but in his own Countrey and among his own Kin, and in his own Houſe,</hi> Mark 6. 4. And He commonly doth the leaſt good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Like as the light of a Candle on a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick, gives light to thoſe further off, but caſts a dark ſhadow next round about it ſelf. Moreover, ye are to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151379:8"/> know. <hi>Not as tho' by our own Power or Holineſs, we can make this Lame Man to walk,</hi> Much leſs to run in the way of Gods Commandments. Nor yet by our own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Wiſdom can we bring any one back into the right way who was gone aſtray. We do utterly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim and Renounce whatſoever is of ſelf, or our own. But yet when He that <hi>Out of the Mouth of Babes and Sucklings hath ordained ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 8. 2. <hi>He that maketh the Dumb,</hi> Exod. 4. 11. And the <hi>Stammering Lips,</hi> Iſa. 28. 11. to ſerve for his own Glory, doth appoint ſuch a weak Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Unworthy Inſtrument, for the Miniſtration of his Word and Truth; Although the Perſon himſelf cannot effect any thing, yet the Word and Truth of God which appears forth through him, <hi>will have its effect,</hi> one way or another, either to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Condemnation, either to make People par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Mercy of God, or to Load them with more Guilt and Ill deſerving, if they will not obey the Word of Life. And tho' this laſt ſeems to be an hard ſaying, yet it is grounded on thoſe Words of the great Preacher of Righteouſneſs, <hi>If I had not come and ſpoken unto them, they had not had ſin, but now they have no Cloke for their ſin,</hi> John 15. 22. And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in behalf of himſelf and of the other Miniſters of the Goſpel, <hi>For we are unto God a ſweet Savour of Chriſt in them that are Saved, and in them that Periſh. To the one, are we the Savour of Death unto Death, and to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Savour of Life unto Life, and VVho is ſufficient for theſe things,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 15, 16. As himſelf doth Anſwer this laſt in the fifth Verſe of the following Chapter, <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God.</hi> And if we are not ſufficient to think, neither are we ſufficient to ſpeak or to do: We are meer Creatures in the hands of God. As in him we live and move and have our Being. So whatever Good Words and True Words do proceed forth from any one, It is what before he had put into our Heart. It is agreeable unto his method and manner of Diſpenſation, to Publiſh and make known his word and will unto the Inhabitants of the Earth; By Men of the like Paſſions and of the ſame Fleſh and Blood with our ſelves. And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151379:9"/> it hath ſo came to paſs, that who have been the greateſt Inſtruments of his Glory, and have received moſt from God of any in their ſeveral Generations; The World hath not known them, but deſpiſed them. Which hath happened not only as to the Ungodly and common ſort. But even ſo it hath been with the Multitude of outward Worſhippers, and who called themſelves the Servants of God. The truth of this obſervation appears from the Hiſtory of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and of his Faithful Miniſters ever ſince, who have been <hi>Workmen approved of God, and not Men pleaſers.</hi> That is to ſay, ſuch who have Faſhioned the Word of God according to the Will and Luſt of the Rich and Mighty People. Which if they had been indeed the Servants of Chriſt, they would not have ſo Learned of him their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For as the Rain cometh down and the Snow from Heaven, and returneth not thither, but Watereth the Earth, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to bring forth and bud; that it may give Seed to the Sower and Bread to the Eater, ſo ſhall my Word be that goeth out of my Mouth: It ſhall not return unto me Void, but it ſhall Accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereto I ſent it,</hi> Iſa. 55. 10, 11. It ſhall Accompliſh either the Salvation or Condemnation of People; It ſhall thus Proſper in the thing whereto God ſends and intends it. That if it doth not reform them, it will leave them more without excuſe. The ſame Word, which now warns them of both, will paſs upon their ſeveral and reſpective Lives and Deaths for all Eternity. Tho' when the Word of God is laid before People and they obey it not, nor do accordingly, then it is thought to be vain, weak and ineffectual; Yet God Himſelf here ſaith, It ſhall not return to him Void; <hi>But whither they will hear, or whither they will forbear, it ſhall be known that there hath been a Prophet among them,</hi> Ezek. 2. Such Words have been made known, or ſuch things have been Written; That they might have turned from their Iniquities, and from the Evil of their doings, which however they were Stifled or Diſregarded in the mean while, ſhall riſe up again at the Judgment of the Great Day. They were warned and teſtified againſt, and his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151379:9"/> Laws were ſet before them; but when they would not take warning, nor yet yield unto him, who by his Word Spirit and Miniſters teſtified againſt them to bring them again to his Law; All theſe and ſuch like are Signs and Prognoſticks that ſuch People will Periſh. It here ſo comes to paſs. <hi>As when Paul expounded and teſtified the Kingdom of God, ſome believed the things which were ſpeketh and ſome believed not,</hi> Acts 28. 23, 24. So it is of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Sermon out of the Word of God, or hearing forth every Teſtimony of Divine Truth, Some obey and give heed unto it, and ſome do not. <hi>Then</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>the Son of</hi> Shealtiel, <hi>and</hi> Joſhua <hi>the Son of</hi> Joſedech <hi>the High Prieſt, with all the Remnant of the People obeyed the Voice of the Lord their God, and the Words of</hi> Haggai <hi>the Prophet (as the Lord had ſent him) and the People did fear before the Lord,</hi> Hag. 1. 12. And ſo we read in <hi>Ezra.</hi> 10. They did obey the Commandment of the Lord, in <hi>Putting away the ſtrange VVives.</hi> But we Read more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of <hi>Kings, Chronicles, Iſaiah, Jeremiah</hi> and in the Evangeliſts; That the Chief and Multitude of the People did not obey, then that they did obey. And yet it was the Word of God which was Preached unto them alſo. But it ſo came to paſs, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled which ſpeak of their Deſtruction. When the Prophet came to <hi>Ananiah</hi> with Words from the Lord, and met with a rough Anſwer from <hi>Ananiah.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>I know that the Lord hath Determined to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou haſt done this, and haſt not hearkened unto my Counſel,</hi> 2 Chron. 25. 16. And ſo it was remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Noted of thoſe that came out againſt the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Battel, <hi>For it was of the Lord to harden their Hearts, that they ſhould come againſt</hi> Iſrael <hi>in Battel, that He might deſtroy them utterly, and that they might have no favour; but that He might deſtroy them as the Lord Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Moſes,</hi> Joſh. 11. 20. And ſo it was Emphatically remarked after that gentle Reproof of <hi>Eli</hi> unto his Sons; <hi>Notwithſtanding, they hearkened not unto the Voice of their Father, becauſe the Lord would ſtay them,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 25. It is juſt the ſame, after all the Preaching and Good Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and Counſel, warning after warning. <hi>Line upon Line, Line upon Line, Precept upon Precept, Precept upon Precept, here a little and there a little.</hi> Notwithſtanding all the things which are contained in the ſtanding writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151379:10"/> Word of God in the Bible; Notwithſtanding all that is Preached and Alledged out from thence every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath and Week Day, throughout the ſeveral Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Places of this <hi>Iſland;</hi> Notwithſtanding all the Reproof and Admonition of Chriſtian Friends and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. And what is yet more and nearer and cloſer unto them, Notwithſtanding all the Accuſings and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of their own Conſcience (which is Gods Witneſs in Man or Woman) yet ſtill, There are a People in the World who will not hearken unto the Voice of all theſe. Tho' it muſt be carefully ſaid as to Temporal Judgments, that they therefore Refuſe and Diſobey, becauſe the Lord would ſlay them. But as to futurity, <hi>The Lord is not willing that any ſhould Periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 9. However, He affording them the means thereof after continued and repeated Provocation, as to that he gives them up at length to themſelves, to their own Hearts Luſts and to walk after their own Counſels, in which they going on will Periſh Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. God hath ſuffered it ſo to be, <hi>That Satan works with all Deceivableneſs in them that Periſh,</hi> which comes upon them through his continued Temptations and Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions.</p>
            <p>I have oftentimes thought that People would never do ſo of themſelves, as now they do in Offending, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, Deſpiſing and Provoking of God, but that an unſeen Enemy doth ſtir them up. Like as it is recorded, <hi>But there was none like unto</hi> Ahab, <hi>which did ſell himſelf to work Wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord, whom</hi> Jeſabel <hi>his Wife did ſtir up,</hi> 1 Kings 21. 25. In the Margent it is Incited. So tho' there is a great deal of Wickedneſs in the Heart of Man, by Reaſon of original and inbred Corruption (for Fleſh and Blood will Imagine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice Evil) Yet this Corrupt Nature would never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and tend ſo far (eſpecially in immediate Rebellion againſt, and Provocation or Deſpiſing of God; for what is ſhewed forth againſt his Word, is againſt God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as it will be found by his Interpretation and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the laſt, tho' perhaps this may be now beſides, and out of the Mind and Intention of the Creatures) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this Infernal <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> whoſe Right Name is <hi>Belzebub</hi> did ſtir and incite them up. <hi>Now the Serpent was more ſubtle then any Beaſt of the Field, which the Lord God had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151379:10"/> made,</hi> Gen. 3. 1: He is more cunning then all, or any of the Sons or Daughters of Men (as they are merely ſuch without the aſſiſtance and direction of Gods Word and Spirit) He tempts, ſuggeſts and doth whatever He can, that each one in particular may loſe Heaven, and fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, He walketh about ſeeking whom He may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. It is his continued Buſineſs and Employment.</p>
            <p>So that it is not altogether ſo much to be wondred at, tho' indeed it is a matter of <hi>Horrour and Grief,</hi> Pſal. 119. 53, 158. and <hi>Sighing,</hi> Ezek. 9. 4. That when God hath made ſuch very ſevere Declarations from Heaven againſt all manner of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, and againſt all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs of Men.</hi> Which alſo will be Executed upon and ſenſibly felt by them after that their Breath is out of their Noſtrils, and their Souls are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from their Bodies; Yet Nevertheleſs in this Time of Provocation and in this Day of Temptation or Trial in this Wilderneſs of the Earth, ſtill People go on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and do the ſame. Yea, rather more Greedily and Earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly then they would have done, if God had revealed no wrath and future Puniſhment againſt the ſame. I knew a Man, who after he had been convinced of the Sin of Unrighteouſneſs, and after He had heard the Word of God declared againſt it; Yet the next opportunity after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, He would more eagerly Practice the ſame. And ſo when the like hath been done to Harlots and Unclean Perſons, the Sin and Danger of their courſe hath been laid open and made known unto them by my Miniſtry of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Word, it hath been told unto me, that at the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e moment, they would for all Practice the leſſer Acts of Laſciviouſneſs: This ſheweth after what manner the Spirit of Diſobedience doth work in the Children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; And when they will of ſet Purpoſe Tranſgreſs yet more and more, in plain and downright oppoſition to the Word of God, and to the Preaching and Miniſtration thereof. <hi>When they will run greedily after the Errour of</hi> Balaam <hi>for Reward,</hi> Jude 11. Or to the Errour of any of their own ways, any Law or Ordinance of God to the contrary Notwithſtanding; <hi>VVhen they will break theſe Bands aſunder, and caſt away theſe Cords from them;</hi> And they will do it the rather, becauſe the Lord by his Word, and Miniſters hath forbidden it. This and ſuch like in the very Truth, ſeems to be that Sin of Preſumption, or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151379:11"/> that <hi>Sinning with an high hand,</hi> whereof it is written, <hi>The Soul which doth Preſumptuouſly, ſhall be cut off from my People ſaith the Lord.</hi> Ay, But the People of the World do not value nor fear that Threatning, for ſuch Perſons who do Preſumptuouſly and Sin with an high hand do commonly live out their appointed Time in Health, Strength, Wealth and Proſperity, as other People do. Yet Alas! In this they are Ignorant or Unmindful, that God hath another Place beſides this Earth, and another time beſides this Life, wherein He will fulfil and make true his Word, <hi>For tho' a Sinner doth Evil an Hundred Times and his Days be Prolonged, yet it ſhall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him,</hi> Ecleſ. 8. 12. <hi>But the ſinner being an Hundred Years Old, ſhall be Accurſed,</hi> Iſa. 65. 20. By which Phraſe of Accurſed, we are given to underſtand that the Word of God doth ſpeak Evil of him now (for ſo <hi>Maledictio</hi> the <hi>Latin</hi> Word for a Curſe, doth ſignify) and it ſhall go Evil with him at the laſt. <hi>VVhen all the Curſes that are written in this Book ſhall be upon him,</hi> Deu. 29. 20. And ſhall be alſo Excuted, and the Lord alſo ſhall <hi>Blot out his Name from under Heaven, ſo that Himſelf ſhall not go there.</hi> This is to be cut off from Gods People, when they ſhall be <hi>Blotted out of the Book of the Living, and not written with the Righteous,</hi> Pſal. 69. 28. So that tho' when He heard the Words of the former Threatning, He bleſſed himſelf in his Heart, ſaying, <hi>I may live as long as other Men and VVomen, tho' I walk in the Imagination of my Heart, to add ſin to my Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſires.</hi> For that is, <hi>Adding Drunkenneſs to Thirſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſmuch as Thirſt is a Lawful and Neceſſary deſire, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as Drunkenneſs is a Sin. So the Courſe of the World goes on, that whereas ſuch and ſuch Thoughts, Words and Actions are Lawful and Neceſſary, People go on to graft and add thereto Vain Thoughts, Falſe Words, and Sinful Actions of their own, whereof there is no need. For as Thirſt may altogether as well, or rather be better quenched and ſatisfied without Annexing Drunkenneſs to it. So People might think, ſpeak and Act altogether as well, yea better, then by conceiving Vanity, ſpeaking forth Falſehood, or Acting of Evil. It is yet ſeven time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a greater Sin, and will make the Oven or Furnace ſeven Times yet hotter, which ſhall be for their Puniſhment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they Tag or Link on an Oath, or Speech of Vain
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151379:11"/> Swearing to an Expreſſion, when the ſentence which they ſpeak would be more perfect and entire without it; Or if to their Actions and Doings, they Annex Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion. Nevertheleſs ſo it hath been, ſo it is, and ſo it will be, during the Time of this Generation. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho at length there will be an End of Tranſgreſſion, <hi>And the Wicked ſhall be no more,</hi> Pſal. 104. 35. For in what Prayer the Spirit of Truth doth dictate, is included a Promiſe that ſo it ſhall be. Yet until theſe latter Days and that Time is come, the World will go on in Sinning, let what will be ſpoken or declared againſt it.</p>
            <p>Herein the <hi>VVord of God hath its Effect;</hi> For hereby it is confirmed, I had almoſt ſaid, ſeen, but I am ſure it is perceived, that there is a Devil, <hi>VVho deceiveth the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deceiveth the whole World,</hi> Rev. 12. 9. <hi>For theſe be the Days of Vengeance, that all things which are written may be fulfilled,</hi> Luke 21. 22. So it is as to the foregoing Sin and Tranſgreſſion, which bring theſe Judgments on the Earth; It muſt needs go on in its courſe, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled, which ſay, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 13. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. That ſome, yea, and the greater part of Mankind ſhall go away into Everlaſting Puniſhment. But as our Lord ſaid concerning offences, <hi>It muſt needs be that offences come. But Wo unto that Man by whom the offence cometh,</hi> Mat. 18. 7. So in like manner it may be here applyed, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled; It muſt needs be that the greater Part of Mankind ſhall go away into Everlaſting Puniſhment. But Wo unto thoſe Particular Souls, who ſhall have their Lot and Portion in this matter; For they can no more ceaſe to be miſerable, then they can ceaſe to be. This is as certain, tho' as yet it is not altogether ſo evident and viſible, then that there is a World which we behold, or an Earth which we tread on: For ſaith the ſame Word, by the which the Heavens and the Earth were Created, and the ſame Truth by the which they are now upheld, and the things therein are Connected together, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but my VVords ſhall not paſs away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' it is imagined and ſaid, that ſeeing is believing. It is an improper Expreſſion, <hi>For faith is the evidence of things not ſeen:</hi> And that which a Man ſeeth, He doth not ſo much believe as know, yet for my Part, when I think of Heat, or Read the 25th Chapter of <hi>Matthew, How that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151379:12"/> all Nations ſhall be Gathered, and Chriſt ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a Shepherd divideth his ſheep from the Goats, and he ſhall ſet the Sheep on the Right hand and the Goats on the left, and ſhall ſay to the one, Come ye Bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c. And to the other, <hi>Go ye Curſed,</hi> I ſay, All this is as evident and manifeſt to me, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I did now ſee that Great and Terrible ſight with my outward Bodily Eyes. And truly, if we did ſee that vaſt and doleful herd of Condemned Criminals, as they are going to the Place of Everlaſting Puniſhment, we ſhould fear. For it is a thing Infinitely more to be Pitied, then now a little Commiſeration doth ariſe, as we behold Sheep or Cattle going to the Shambles and Slaughter Houſe. What God hath ſaid by his Son Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to paſs: So that this will as certainly be as if we now ſaw it with our Eyes. For it will as certainly be in the appointed Time, as that we now preſent, were once living on the Earth. What can be more forcible to make us take the utmoſt heed that our ſelves be not among them?</p>
            <p>It would be an hard Caſe, if there was not one in ſuch a Pariſh or Neighbourhood, who ſhould go to Heaven. But I truſt that ſeveral will, as I am aſſured from the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>That all thoſe will who have a Good Conſcience, and are willing to live honeſtly in all things,</hi> Heb. 13. 18. So it would be Melancholly and Diſmal to ſuppoſe. But yet it is juſtly and truly to be feared, that ſome in this Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, I do not know one of them, but the Lord knows who the very Perſons be that are in ſuch a place now; Who ſhall be found amongſt thoſe <hi>Goats,</hi> at the very laſt Day. But either to convince them thereof, or to make it known unto them, would make their Life hang in doubt, and fill them with a <hi>fearful Expectation,</hi> and give them a trembling heart: So to point them out by their Names and Diſtinct Perſons, it would make all Chriſtians, <hi>Note that Man or Woman,</hi> and have no <hi>Converſation with them,</hi> If he or ſhe ſhould prove certainly a caſt away, or a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Creature at that Day. But every one would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid or ſhy of them in the mean while (as now they are of a Man that is to be hanged or put to Death) I do here ſomewhat allude to thoſe Words of the Apoſtle, <hi>If any Man obey not the Word of this Epiſtle, Note that Man, and have no Converſation with him that he be aſhamed.</hi> So if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151379:12"/> any Man or Woman amongſt ye do not obey thoſe things, which have been here alledged unto ye from the Word of the Lord; If there be any who will deſpiſe and go <hi>frow ardly in the way of their heart.</hi> And further, if there be any who ſhall do Preſumptuouſly and Sin with an high hand, as of ſet Purpoſe, to Sin and Tranſgreſs more and more, becauſe ſuch things have been ſpoken againſt that, and all manner of Sin and Tranſgreſſion; Truly, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Partakers of the ſame Fleſh and Blood, theſe and ſuch like are ſad Signs and Prognoſticks, that ſuch very Perſons will be indeed found among that Number of Goats at the laſt Day, and to them I am now ſent with heavy Tid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>It would be good for them if they had never been Born;</hi> And upon them this Word Preached and Publiſhed will have its effect (like the Sun which doth melt Wax, but harden Clay) for Evil, but not for Good. And here People ſhould not ſo much as keep Company with ſuch, ſo as to Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in their Evil Deeds, or ſo much as barely to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance them in their Rebellion, Tranſgreſſion, or even in their Contempt of the Lord God; But only to warn, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and teſtify, that they ſeeing themſelves as it were cut off from the Society of Mankind, by perceiving the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience and Miſery thereof, may underſtand the ten Thouſand Times greater Miſery to be cut off and depriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>General Aſſembly and Church of the firſt Born which are Written in Heaven; And from God the Judge of all, and the Spirits of juſt Men made Perfect.</hi> And this would be ſome means for them to turn out of the wrong way which leads unto Deſtruction; <hi>And they may be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Tranſgreſſing without a cauſe,</hi> Pſal. 25. 3. Or, that they ſhould ever deſpiſe the Lord their God.</p>
            <p>It was aforeſaid, that the foregoing Sin and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which bring theſe Judgments on the Earth muſt needs go on in its Courſe that the Scriptures might be fulfilled. What are theſe Judgments? They are declared in <hi>Math.</hi> 24. and <hi>Luke 21. Rumors, ſtirs and commotions of Wars, Nation againſt Nation, and Great Earthquakes ſhall be in Divers Places,</hi> Luke 21. 11. And there was a Great Earthquake in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July,</hi> 1692. There was an Univerſal ſhaking of the Earth throughout moſt Parts of <hi>Europe</hi> in <hi>September,</hi> 1692. And in <hi>January,</hi> 1692. There was the Greateſt Earthquake in the <hi>Iſlands</hi> of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Malta,</hi> ſo as to ſwallow up an Hundred and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151379:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151379:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151379:14"/> Six ſcore Thouſand Inhabitants, then ever I heard or read of in Hiſtory ſince Man was Created on the Earth. Theſe are <hi>Great Earthquakes in Divers Places, and Fearful Sights, and Great Signs there have been from Heaven;</hi> As the Great Comet about eighteen Years ago, which is no long Time according to the Courſe and Reckoning of Time in the Decree of God, and according to Scripture Account. And for ought we know, that gentle Univerſal ſhaking of the Earth in <hi>England, France, Holland,</hi> or the Low Countreys; Wherein it is more obſervable, and ſhews that the Hand of God is ſomewhat more in it, then the ordinary Courſe of Nature: Becauſe it happened thus at the very ſame Minute of Time in other Places, which were diſtinct and ſeparated one from another by the Great and Wide Sea; All this may be a forerunner of a much Greater Earthquake, from which we are no more ſecured and abſolutely preſerved by the Advantage of our Countreys Scituation, and becauſe ſuch things have not been ſo uſually among us as among others, <hi>For the Pillars of the Earth are the Lords, and he hath ſet the World upon them. For He who ſtretcheth the</hi> North <hi>over the empty Place, and hangeth the Earth upon nothing,</hi> Can find out this way to Puniſh us if he pleaſe. As it is yet more certain, that tho if the Earth ſhould not ſwallow us up alive, yet it is but a very little while, and it will receive and devour our Dead Bodies, as alſo it gives Aſſurance of what he hath promiſed, which hath been in ſome meaſure already, and is yet to be fulfilled, <hi>Saying, Yet once more I ſhake not the Earth, but alſo Heaven,</hi> Hag. 2. 6. Heb. 12. 26. Which is not only ſet forth by way of Greatneſs of Expreſſion, or to ſignify only the Men and Women contained therein; but it ſhall reach and affect even the very Elemental Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, even the whole Creation according to 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. As our ſelves ſhall one Day ſee; All one as we now hear, that thoſe foregoing ſigns are fulfilled. And as at ſuch a Seaſon of the Year, we behold all the Trees ſhoot forth and the Graſs doth grow, then we know of our ſelves that Summer is near at hand; <hi>So likewiſe when ye ſee theſe things come to paſs, know ye that the Kingdom of God is nigh at hand.</hi> Now it is nearer then ever it was yet. But we are given to underſtand farther, that by the more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appearance of theſe foregoing ſigns, we are juſt entring upon, if not falling into thoſe Great and Glorious Times.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151379:14"/> Whereof the Scriptures do abundantly ſpeak that it ſhall be in the latter Days, that the Great Things of God ſhall be fulfilled. And tho' Chriſt ſaid Sixteen Hundred Years ago, <hi>This Generation ſhall not paſs away till all theſe things ſhall be fulfilled</hi> (By which kind of Expreſſion faith is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and proved, as alſo the underſtandings of Men are ſomewhat Puzzled) yet take and include Chriſt himſelf into that Generation (for he was then in the Days of his Fleſh, and a Generation includes all that are living there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) and it holds literally true in that ſence, for He the Son of God hath not paſſed away, <hi>But was without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Days or End of Life, but abideth continually.</hi> But I do verily believe, That tho' there is never a Chriſt now on Earth, nor an <hi>Enoch,</hi> nor yet any ſuch of whom there is a ſaying, <hi>That any now living ſhall not die;</hi> Yet before all the Young Men and Children, and Infants, that are now Breathing on this Earth are gone off from it, there will be yet ſomewhat a Greater and more extraordinary Manifeſtation concerning the Kingdom of God, then hath been in all the mean Generations, ſince Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were on the Earth. And this I do aſſuredly gather, becauſe the Time of the <hi>Promiſe draws nigh,</hi> Acts 7. 17. As is Manifeſt from the yet greater Appearance and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſneſs of thoſe foregoing ſigns here mentioned.</p>
            <p>All this put together ſhould induce us to lay theſe things to heart, and to tremble and fear continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, for what he hath already done on the Earth, as alſo out of Expectation of what he will do yet further. Which Expectation our hearts ſhould be always very full off, and in no wiſe Choke and Stifle the ſence thereof with <hi>Gluttony, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Cares of this Life, and ſo that Day come upon you unawares,</hi> Luke 21. 34. Which is brought in upon this occaſion. As <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid upon that terrible ſight at Mount <hi>Sinah, I exceedingly fear and quake:</hi> So the ſame mind ſhould be at all Times and in all Places, in all the Servants of God, as to what they have heard or ſeen, He hath done more lately, is now a doing, and will ſhortly bring yet greater things to paſs, then all theſe in this Earth, the lower Part of the World.</p>
            <p>As God at firſt made all things, and doth now uphold them by the Word of his Power: ſo ſome of them do move and go on according to his Will, Appointment and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151379:15"/> Decree. Known to God are all his Works from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World, and ſo it is as to what He will do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the End thereof, as our ſelves know what we intend to do at ſuch a Time hereafter, if we have the ſame Mind and Will, Strength and Opportunity, Life and Power of Action, or ſuch like. The want of any of which do often cauſe a neglect or failure of the ſame. But now with God, there is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning, He is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and Eternal. What He once Decrees, Purpoſes or Wills, he doth certainly bring to paſs; and he ſpeaks of things before they are done, <hi>While they are yet Springing up do I tell you of them.</hi> And ſo it is, when he ſpeaks of things before-hand, and they do afterwards come to paſs in like manner, then it is, that his word is fulfilled. There are a Thouſand Inſtances of this in Scripture, and ſo very many, for the whole is but an orderly Declaration of ſuch things, that it is ſuperfluous to mention Particulars.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who know ſomewhat more of God, then the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and common Multitude, do apprehend, perceive and obſerve, that as all things are Gods, from the <hi>Cedar</hi> in <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the <hi>Hyſſop</hi> on the Wall, from the greateſt to the ſmalleſt; for his Providence and Government of things is comprehenſive of and extenſive, even unto ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and the hairs of our head, the more inconſiderable Creatures, and every leaſt thing that belongs to us; All one as to Angels or Men, or to the yet greater Works of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So as that ſame Word in Scripture doth ſpeak of all things that are done on this Earth: So Reciprocally what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done or comes to paſs or happens here, it is all a fulfilling of the ſame Word. There is hardly any thing whatever, be it of greater or leſs moment, but ſome Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Book of the Lord do ſpeak thereof either in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Words, or near to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>There ſhall the great Owl make her Neſt, and lay and hatch, and gather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her ſhadow: There ſhall the Vultures alſo be gathered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one with her Mate. Seek ye out of the Book of the Lord and Read, No one of theſe ſhall fail, no one ſhall want her Mate; for my mouth it hath Commanded, and his Spirit it hath gathered them,</hi> Iſa. 34. 15, 16. As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Doth God take care for Oxen?</hi> So doth his Word ſpeak of Cormorants, and Bitterns and Ravens, Wild Beaſts and Satyrs, Schreech Owls and Great Owls, and Vultures and Thorns, and Nettles and Brambles? Yes, verily it doth, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151379:15"/> of all the things in the Earth, and even of the very Times and Seaſons of the Year, <hi>How Graſs doth grow upon the Mountains and Herb for the uſe of Man.</hi> Obſerve this laſt, which leads again towards our Subject and Intended mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For as the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> goes on to add, <hi>Saith He it altogether for our ſakes? For our ſakes, no doubt this is VVritten,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 10. So as there is a certain Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Linking on together of all the Creatures and Works of God (whither Living or Inanimate) So they have each ſeverally, and all together a yet greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, Tendency and Relation to us Men and Women. It is ſo Written of them, and ſo Gods ſpeaks of them in his word, for our ſakes, in order to us, as they are ſomewhat concerned, and do belong unto the Exerciſe and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Kingdom and Dominion over Men: He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God unto whom we and all the other Creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, have to do. It is but a ſmall matter as to theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward viſible preſent things, <hi>But the Kingdom of God is within you;</hi> And the chief and only matter is as each ſtands in Subordination, Subſerviency and Tendency to the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and future State of things; and that is Branched out only one of theſe two ways, Salvation or Condemnation, Happineſs or Miſery.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Word of God hath its effect,</hi> upon all Men and Women of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Countrey, Nation and Language, from the beginning of their Generations unto the End thereof, one of theſe two ways, <hi>Go ye into all the World and Preach the Goſpel to every Creature. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is Baptized, ſhall be ſaved; and He that believeth not, ſhall be Damned,</hi> Mark 16. 15, 16. He that obeyeth all the whole Word of God ſhall be ſaved; but He that obeyeth not the Word of God ſhall be Damned. <hi>He that obſerves all things whatſoever Chriſt hath Commanded, Chriſt will be a Saviour unto him,</hi> But He that doth not obſerve all things whatſoever Chriſt hath Commanded, He is without the Covenant and Benefit of a Saviour; and He ſhall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh. <hi>For the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven in flaming Fire, taking Vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Who ſhall be Puniſhed with Everlaſting Deſtruction, from the Preſence of the Lord and the Glory of his Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is Reported of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who was in his Generation a Preacher unto a very Numerous Auditory in the City of <hi>Antioch. (Where the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians,</hi> And I would to God, they had never been called any thing elſe ſince) that He ſhould ſay, that if He was to Preach before all the Men and Women liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Earth, and ſuch a thing were poſſible for them all to be gathered together, and his Voice could reach them all (as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151379:16"/> ſuch a thing might be now effected by Printing and an Univerſal Publication of the ſeveral Copies, which would be a very good work if it were ſo done) He would chooſe for his Text theſe Words, <hi>O ye Sons of Men, How long will ye turn my Glory into ſhame? How long will ye Love Vanity and ſeek after leaſing? Selab,</hi> Pſal. 4. 2. So if the like was here to be ſuppoſed, as indeed it might be of good effect if it were ſo done, there could not be a more proper Subject choſen then what hath been here inſiſted on, To ſhew, <hi>How that the Word of God will have its effect, upon thoſe Multitudes, Multitudes in the Valley of Deciſion,</hi> Joel 3. 14. So as to decide their future State and Condition one way or another. As the Proverb is among the <hi>Latins, Ye may gueſs at the Bigneſs of Hercules by his Foot:</hi> So we may make ſome eſtimate of this Generation of Men and Women now living upon the Earth, by ſuch a mixt Multitude Aſſembled together of Saints and Sinners. As there are probably of both ſorts, ſo it is abroad in all Pariſhes of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo in all the other Habitable Parts of the Earth. <hi>Some will believe the things that have been ſpoken, and ſome will believe them not.</hi> Some will obey theſe Words, and ſome will obey them not. And Perhaps, of this latter ſort, ſome will be found, who will ſin yet more Violently and Earneſtly, and Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, becauſe ſuch Words of Soberneſs and Truth, have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto them. They will make (if they can) the Preacher a Liar; and what lies in them, the Word of God of none effect. As if it was not able and ſufficient to Convert Sinners from the Errour of their ways, in that themſelves are reſolved not to be Converted by it. There be thoſe abroad in the World, who do not Hear or Read this; and if they do not altogether ſo perverſely and obſtinately againſt the Word Preached, for they hear little or none at all; and it may be out of a ſecret Conſciouſneſs, that their own Lives are not Anſwerable thereunto, nor yet will they Regulate their Life and Manners according to it; and they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that then to Hear or Read the Word of God, will but ſo much the more increaſe their Sin and Guilt. Theſe do not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how that the Height and Abomination of Iniquity is ſet forth throughout the Old Teſtament; <hi>In refuſing to Hear Gods Words,</hi> The Spirit it ſelf calleth them, <hi>This Evil People which refuſe to hear my Words,</hi> Jer. 13. 10. (Which I would, were more attended unto even by the very Worſhippers of God) that when an opportunity is given, or Door is open to hear the Word Preached, they count it a matter indifferent, they may hear or let it alone. But let ſuch know, <hi>That when the Dead ſmall and great, ſhall ſtand before God,</hi> They ſhall remember, and find that it was matter of Duty for them to have heard, and not as a thing of Indifferency, which carries along with it a Contempt and Neglect of the things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his Kingdom. It will be then ſeen which way doth moſt pleaſe and ſhall find Acceptance with God, as alſo whither the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151379:16"/> Preſumptuous ſinner doth not yet more diſpleaſe and provoke him by thoſe his Imaginations. But even in thoſe who are moſt Ignorant and keep away from the ſight and hearing of his Word; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, God hath not left himſelf without Witneſs, for they have a certain Rumour and Notion, or rather an apprehenſion of the things contained in the Bible. They have many ſilent and ſerious thoughts within themſelves; and when theſe do reprove, warn and Teſtify, they do in like manner Preſumptouſly againſt them, as others do immediately againſt the word Preached. But where is that degree of the Spirit of Contradiction, and that utmoſt Height of Diſobedience, To do after their own Luſt and Will, any Law or Ordinance of God to the contrary Notwithſtanding. For the Language of Stubbornneſs ſpeaks on this wiſe, <hi>I have Loved ſtrangers, and after them I will go.</hi> This makes their ſin to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſinful in the mean while, and ſuch ſhall be beaten with more ſtripes, and Inherit a greater Condemnation at the laſt.</p>
            <p>The Prophet doth intend ſomewhat alike to what it afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, when he uſeth that Phraſe and kind of words. <hi>Hearken unto mee ye Stouthearted that are far from Righteouſneſs.</hi> Iſa. 46. 12. <hi>Stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted,</hi> ſuch as will not ſubmit as it were out of a Piece of Pride and Bravery, and they do of ſet purpoſe keep off. <hi>I bring near my Righteouſneſs, it ſhall not be far off and my Salvation ſhall not tarry.</hi> Verſ. 13. But they will go further off and ſtand more at a diſtance and delay yet more that they may not ſee it. A perverſe and contrary manner of Acting, which God doth behold and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe upon them.</p>
            <p>There are ſome who let God do what He will, ſend forth his Light and make further Manifeſtations of his Truth, give more Preſſing Motives and Arguments, ſend his ſeveral ſorts of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet they will not return unto the Lord. And ſo Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his methods of Mercy and Truth, when there are Great Multitudes already brought over and Converted, yet they reckon it as it were a greater Piece of Gallantry and Honour, that for all this they will not be perſwaded. <hi>Who in the Land of uprightneſs will deal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njustly, and will not behold the Majesty of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 26. 10. In that exceeding Glory of the Church, by the vaſt Multitude of the Gentiles coming in, yet ſtill ſome will be Rebellious, yea, and refuſe to come. And therefore is that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation and Threatning put as it were juſt in the middle of all thoſe Bleſſings and Promiſes, <hi>For the Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve thee ſhall Periſh; Yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted,</hi> Iſa. 60. 12. If that be their Humour and Reſolution, ſo it may be to kick againſt the Pricks, to run their Head violently againſt a Braſs Wall, to ſet themſelves as it were againſt their God. When He hath Propheſied and Foretold of ſuch an Univerſal Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they will what lieth in them, make God a Liar, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will ſtill refuſe to be reformed. O Wicked Fools! Poor
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151379:17"/> Ignorant Souls! This ye cannot do, but confirm his Word the more, for his Holy Spirit doth foreſee this Stubbornneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractinorineſs of Yours, and ſpeaks of it ſome Thouſand Years before your ſelves Practice it, <hi>That the Purpoſe of God might stand,</hi> And what Himſelf hath ſaid ſhall be fulfilled. Nevertheleſs, for your Evil Intent and Malice of Heart, you ſhall ſmart and be Puniſhed for the ſame. <hi>They ſhall Periſh and be utterly waſted;</hi> And then themſelves ſhall know whither it would not have been better for them to have ſerved God, (then as they did) to have went on in their own Perverſeneſs and Oppoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After all, What ſhall I ſay? God hath ſpoken thus, and himſelf ſhall do accordingly. I ſhall go ſoftly, all my Years in the Bitterneſs of my Soul.</hi> As often as I do ſeriouſly and throughly reflect thereon, I have great heavineſs and continual Sorrow of Heart. I do not ſpeak this in Words of Courſe, or only in Scripture Phraſe; But from an inward feeling of the ſame, and from the very Truth of the matter. For tho' I could never wiſh my ſelf Accurſed from Chriſt, rather then that my Brethren and Kinſmen according to the Fleſh ſhould Periſh. I have had yet a much greater concern for my neareſt Kindred according to the Fleſh (Altho' herein, <hi>They have Rewarded me Evil for Good, and Hatred for my Love,</hi> Pſal. 109. 10.) Then for the reſt of my Brethren and Siſters of the common ſtock of Mankind. Yet herein, I ſay the Truth in Chriſt I lie not, my Conſcience alſo bearing me Witneſs in the Holy Ghoſt, that I have ſeveral times wiſhed that my ſelf had never came forth into Being, rather then I ſhould know and ſee ſo many of my fellow Creatures, who are Fleſh of my Fleſh, and Bone of my Bone, go away into Everlaſting Puniſhment and Miſery. I have had that greateſt Compaſſion and moſt Earneſt ſenſible concern for them. For as it is Proverbially ſpoken of very ill weather <hi>That one would not then have a Dog abide out of Doors:</hi> So Eternal Damnation is ſuch a Terrible and Miſerable thing to them, who believe and apprehend it throughly, that one would not wiſh it to the greateſt Enemy one had. I muſt confeſs again, that this great Compaſſion and Earneſt concern, which I have formerly had for others, doth now go off and leſſen with me. And what may ſeem yet more ſtrange, It doth ſo even as I behold their continued Provocation and Repeated evil doing; which will more certainly ſeal them over unto the Day of their Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>In this Temper of Mind I come yet more near to that of the Spirit, which ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>Yet behold therein ſhall be left a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that ſhall be brought forth, both Sons and Daughters. Behold, they ſhall come forth unto you, and ye ſhall ſee their way, and their doings: And ye ſhall be comforted concerning the evil that I have brought upon</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>even concerning all that I have brought upon it. And they ſhall comfort you when ye ſee their ways and their doings: And ye ſhall know that I have not done without cauſe, all that I have done in it, ſaith the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151379:17"/> Lord God,</hi> Ezek. 14. 22, 23. There is ſo very much Malignity and Evil deſerving in Sin, that when God Himſelf (which the Miniſters of his Word do very faintly and imperfectly now) ſhall lay it open before his Saints and Servants, <hi>As that they ſhall ſee their ways and their doings,</hi> As we behold Dirt and Mire now, even they ſhall be Comforted concerning all the Puniſhment and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which he will lay upon the Inhabitants of the Earth, tho' it be upon their own Father, Mother, Brothers, Siſters, the Wife of their Boſom, the neareſt Kinsfolks and Deareſt Friends according to the Fleſh. So that they ſhall not Pity the tender and delicate Man, who was moſt ſet out with Riches, Beauty, Good Breeding, or common good Nature (if it was mixt with Ungodlineſs or Contempt of God) <hi>Nor yet the tender and delicate Woman, which would not adventure to ſet the ſole of her foot upon the ground for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licateneſs and Tenderneſs,</hi> Deut. 28. 56. And How then will ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo ſo much Pain and Fire? <hi>And ye ſhall know that I have not done without cauſe</hi> (without their deſerving of it) which we ſhall more clearly perceive then tho' we cannot now; but we are apt to think it hard that Mankind ſhould dye Eternally for taſting a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Honey, or for the Pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon) <hi>all that I have done in it,</hi> even in his utmoſt Vengeance and Everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith the Lord God, <hi>Can thine heart endure, or can thine hands be ſtrong in the Days that I ſhall deal with thee? I the Lord have ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it, and I will do it,</hi> Ezek. 22. 14. By the former Part of which Expreſſion is ſhewh forth, that God will overcome their former Stubbornneſs and Preſumption, By the Puniſhment He will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, that He will get the Victory and make them to yield. In the latter part is the Ratification and Confirmation of it, <hi>I the Lord have ſpoken it, and I will do it.</hi> As to all that foregoing Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Rebellion of the <hi>Jeres, Wherein they denied the Holy one and the just, and deſired a Murtherer to be granted unto them and killed the Prince of Life,</hi> How doth <hi>Peter</hi> lay it before them and Aſſign the cauſe thereof? <hi>And now Brethren, I wot that through Ignorance, ye did it, as alſo did your Rulers. But thoſe things which God hath ſhewed by the Mouth of all his Prophets that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer, He hath ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> Acts 3. 17, 18. When Himſelf was in the midſt of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, He ſaith, <hi>Thinkeſt thou that I cannot Pray my Father, and He ſhall preſently give me more then twelve Legions of Angels.</hi> (Who would have preſerved and defended him from all thoſe Wicked Men that were his Crucifiers) <hi>But how then ſhall the Scriptures be fulfilled; that thus it muſt be,</hi> Mat. 26. 53, 54. In like manner as to all that ſin, Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion, which God hath ſpoken of by the Mouth of all his Prophets, Evangeliſts and Apoſtles; It muſt needs go on in its Courſe, <hi>That the Scriptures might be fulfilled,</hi> Both as to that and alſo to the further end and conſequent thereof, <hi>When He ſhall Puniſh the World for their Evil, and the Wicked for their Iniquity;</hi> And that will be found true alſo, <hi>Which ſpeaks of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151379:18"/> Wide Gate and Broad way that leadeth to Deſtruction, and many there be who go in thereat, Mat.</hi> 7. 13. Amalek, <hi>was the firſt of the Nations, but his latter end ſhall be that he Periſh for Ever,</hi> Numbers 23. 20. Tho' they are in the firſt, higheſt and moſt proſperous Wordly State, thſs hinders not, but rather ſooner occaſions, that they be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for ever, as we Learn from ſundry other Places of the Word of Truth.</p>
            <p>The Scripture doth ſtand Checquer wiſe, if I may ſo expreſs it. It is made up of black and white, for therein is an intermixture of Promiſes and Threatnings, Good and Evil things, <hi>Bleſſing and Curſing, Life and Death.</hi> It is ſo almoſt in every Chapter. I ſhall inſtance in one, and mention the ſame uſe thereof that is there macle. And as the Spirit of God doth make mention of the <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Orator,</hi> Iſa. 3. 3. It is a neceſſary part of Oratory to leave ſomething with the Hearers at laſt, that it may ſurely ſtick and he remembred by them. At the cloſe of this Diſcourſe, I would obſerve unto ye, how, that in the Tenth Chapter of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> there is an intermixture of Threatnings and Promiſes, Good and Evil things, for there is mention made, <hi>Of a fearful looking for of Judgment and of Fiery Indignation which ſhall devour the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord. And again, The Lord ſhall judge his People, it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the Living God.</hi> After all theſe terrible things to the Wicked and Ungodly, The Apoſtle ſpeaks in a more mild ſtrain unto the Chriſtians, <hi>Knowing in your ſelves, that in Heaven ye have a better and an enduring ſubſtance, and of a great Recompence of reward,</hi> ver. 35. <hi>After ye have done the Will of God, ye might receive the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> ver. 36. But amidſt and in the concluſion of all, He ſhews himſelf to be a faithful and skillful Workman, dividing the Word of Truth aright, and giving to every one his Portion, for he ſaith, <hi>Now the juſt ſhall live by Faith, but if any Man draw back. My Soul ſhall have no Pleaſure in him. But we are not of them who draw back into Perdition, but of them who believe unto the ſaying of the Soul.</hi> So People are to take and receive in by Faith, all the things that have been afore-written. <hi>They muſt live by Faith, if they will be juſtified and ſaved.</hi> But if any of <hi>ye draw back,</hi> that is, go off and recede from his Truths, neither God, nor yet any of his Saints and Servants will have any Pleaſure in that Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. But by the Divine Grace and Aſſiſtance, it ſhall be my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and continued endeavour throughout all the remaining Days of this Life of Vanity, as I hope, and do hereby exhort that it may be of others alſo, that we be not found amongſt them, upon whom the Word of God will have its effect to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but not to Salvation; But rather that ye and my ſelf (there is nothing in the World which I ſo much deſire) may be found amongſt them, who ſhall <hi>believe to the ſaving of the Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
